<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ballance adjvsted, or, The interest of church and state weighed and considered upon this revolution</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13181437</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13181437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98365</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98365)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 445:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Ballance adjvsted, or, The interest of church and state weighed and considered upon this revolution</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98365:1"/>
            <head>THE <hi>BALLANCE ADJ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STED:</hi> Or, the Intereſt of Church and State Weighed and Conſidered upon this REVOLUTION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am heartily glad to find by your Letter, that the <hi>State-Prodigal,</hi> the <hi>Vindiciae Juris Regii,</hi> and ſome other things have brought you ſo far on your way back. I doubt not but to cloſe up thoſe other points upon which you heſitate, that you may eaſily and heartily return to your Duty to God, your King and your Country; to all which this unhappy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution has done moſt manifeſt diſhonour and wrong. I find the loſſe at Sea by extraordinary Storms, as well as by the Enemy, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Deſtruction of your Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by Famine and Peſtilance, two of the ſharpeſt Arrows in the Almighty's Quiver, in a manner ſo full of horror and conſternation; while the King has health and plenty in his Quarters and Cities; has brought you to a juſt apprehenſion that the hand of God is againſt you, who once did diſtinguiſh betwixt the Land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Egypt,</hi> betwixt the houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> when the Deſtroying Angel went forth. The reſpect I have for you, makes me not able to diſſemble my ſatisfaction that you your ſelf now think your Chariot Wheels of, and that you ought no longer to oppoſe that Providence, which is not at a ſtand, as ſome ſay, but by remarkable inſtances declares it ſelf for the contrary Party.</p>
            <p>You are much in the right, that you now conclude, we either were not in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Popery under King <hi>James,</hi> or that we are not more ſecure, nay, not ſo ſafe from it now.</p>
            <p>The King never, as could be learnt, declared that he would bring it in, but ſomething like the contrary. We muſt not think a Toleration, or taking off the Penal Laws (tho they are ſuch good Fences and Bulwarks as Church-of-<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>-men ſhould not part with) to be ſetting up Popery. All Diſſenters deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and have now got ſo much for themſelves, and the King for his party ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſired more; and with this remarkable difference, that he deſired Law for what he did, but our New Governours do the ſame thing without it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98365:2"/>
            <p>The Truth is, I wonder many more beſides you, have not taken Check at ſo manifeſt a Paradox, That the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould go about to ſet up Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery in a Nation which has all the horrible apprehenſions of it, that an Idea of the Beaſt in the <hi>Revelations</hi> can create; and at the ſame time that the Pope, that man of Sin, ſhould engage all his Adherents in a Confederacy, and uſe his utmoſt endeavours to pull it down, or to protect us from it.</p>
            <p>You ſay well that you cannot find what new Security we have gotten for our Religion upon this Revolution, it being a plain undeniable matter of Fact, declared and boaſted of by Mr. <hi>H</hi>—and others, and proved by many overt Acts, That the P. of O's enterprize was firſt projected in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, a Prince that was firm enough to our Religion, that it was built and ſupported upon the Popes Intereſt and Authority in the Confederacy, who about <hi>May</hi> laſt, ſent a Nuncio to Congratulate the Succeſs, and that the P. of <hi>O.</hi> that Glorious Pillar of the Reformation, and the Mighty Deliverer of our Church and State, did promiſe the Pope to preſerve the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> in the Exerciſe of their Religion, and purſuant to his promiſe, did cauſe the Prieſts to be ſet at Liberty throughout <hi>England,</hi> tho many good well known Proteſtants were kept in Gaol contrary to our Laws, and the Fundamentals of our Conſtitution. Theſe things you ſay well, have raiſed ſuch a miſt in your Eyes, that you cannot as yet perceive any ſecurity at all to our Religion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any body elſe, as I believe, except the Old Woman, who for a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band could ſee the Egg upon the top of it, tho ſhe could not ſee the Barn.</p>
            <p>You may well wonder, upon ſecond thoughts, why we ſhould have been under ſuch diſmal fears of Popery, under King <hi>James,</hi> becauſe no man can make another a Papiſt whether he will or no. A man cannot change or alter his own belief at pleaſure, much leſs can another do it for him, without conviction. I never heard that K. <hi>James</hi> ever offered to ſay much for his Religion, and I have more ground to preſume the P. of <hi>O.</hi> has leſs to ſay againſt it; and for what the Prieſts can do, they have as much liberty, and ſome more advantage now, than they had under King <hi>James,</hi> unleſs it can be imagined that wearing their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits may have as ſtrong Charms againſt Hereſie, as ſome ſay it has againſt the Devil.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, if this Revolution had not abundantly proved, that to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt unreaſonable Fears, and boundleſs Ambitions, or inſatiable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges, is to Row againſt Wind and Tide: I would give my ſelf leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large a little upon the patience and conſtancy of the Primitive Chriſtians, who by their ſufferings gave life and honour to their Religion, and propagated their Faith by ſhedding their Blood; and upon the Martyrdom of our firſt Reformers under Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which certainly perfected and eſtabliſhed the Reformation, in the beginning of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> inſomuch that as the Laws of our Holy Religion oblige us to adhere to the Truth, however perſecuted or deſpiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Guliel. Nubrigenſis <hi>of the Uſurpat. of K.</hi> Stephen.</note> and under the higheſt Penalties forbid us to debauch or corrupt it for any Intereſt or Security; ſo I would here have given ſome inſtances, even in our own Kingdom, how much men have been diſappointed, who have gone about to cover with a covering, but not of God, to provide for their own ſecurity, as not daring to truſt the iſſue of things with God: But as the Corruptneſs of the time gives me occaſion to believe ſuch Harrangues would not be very ſucceſsful, ſo your caſe makes them leſs needful, and therefore I will haſten on.</p>
            <p>Thus far you ſay you are ſatisfied, and ſo may all the world be, that the Pope was the Head of the Confederacy; that the Revolution was in Agitation before K. <hi>C.</hi> ended his Reign; that <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Rebellion was but an Eſſay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, he taking his leave of the P. at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and the ſcattered Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Enterprize finding there Succour and Maintenance, and being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the P. of <hi>O</hi>'s beſt Friends,<note place="margin">Inſtance in Sir <hi>Rob. Payton</hi>'s Caſe.</note> and ſuch as endeavoured to ſeize and bring any of them to Juſtice, reckoned his Enemies; that the Fanaticks, who are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98365:2"/>deep in our new Government, when they made ſuch Addreſſes to the King, offering their Lives and Fortunes, intended to betray him. And laſtly, you own your ſelf to be fully convinced, that the P. of <hi>O.</hi> came, notwithſtanding his Declaration, with a deſign to Dethrone his Father, and to Uſurp his Crown, becauſe there are unexceptionable Witneſſes to depoſe, that above three years ſince the Favourites at the <hi>Hague</hi> were adviſing with their Friends what places to put in for at Court, when the P. of <hi>O.</hi> came to be King, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impoſſible for ſuch forward Spirits to look at Reverſions after his Death, ſince the King has neither Old Age, nor <hi>Aſtma,</hi> nor any other Infirmities upon him, that might give them that occaſion. And I will give you another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that you are not miſtaken about his Intentions. At <hi>Shirbourn Caſtle His Highneſs made a ſolemn promiſe of ſome Eccleſiaſtical preferments to a Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who being reſolved to put in time enough, there made his Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe, and many more ſuch like accounts, you ſay you are very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Revolution ſtands upon a Foundation which has no mixture in it of Honour or Honeſty; but yet you dare ſcarce entertain the thought of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Revolution for fear of the <hi>French,</hi> and leſt the Nation ſhould loſe the comfort and advantage of good Neighbourhood, and Alliance with the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I think, if I ſet you right in theſe two points, your way is quite cleared, and I ſuppoſe I ſhall do that, if I make out upon the Square theſe following things: 1. That our King would not make any uſe of the <hi>French</hi> to annoy us: 2. If he would, the <hi>French</hi> would not aſſiſt him in it: 3. That all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief we could apprehend from the <hi>French,</hi> and much more, we ſhall ſuffer from the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay the King would not offer to bring the <hi>French</hi> upon us, to annoy us, and eſpecially in our Religion, becauſe it is againſt all the Common and known Rules of Policy, for any Prince who is at Peace at home, to call in any Foreigners, becauſe they always Plunder and Ravage the Nation, and throw the people into a diſcontenting fear, and a neglect of Trade, and then twenty to one, but they make a prey of the Prince that invited them, when he is weaken'd by the Poverty and Diſaffection of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt conclude the King would not bring in a <hi>French</hi> Army, becauſe he harbour'd and cheriſh'd with a Princely Compaſſion and Charity, all thoſe <hi>Hugonots</hi> who in very great numbers came over from <hi>France.</hi> We ſee by Experience, they would have born Arms againſt him, and the King would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have received them whom he might have well kept back, without diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting the Nation, which according to the Spirit then up, was unwilling enough to entertain them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we muſt believe the King would never have offered to bring in any <hi>French</hi> Army upon us, becauſe of his own meer <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> he procured (when he was D. of <hi>York</hi>) a Repeal of the Statute <hi>De Comburendo Haeretico,</hi> a Law which would have done his buſineſs, even without the <hi>French,</hi> if he would have been at that work.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we may conclude, without Impeachment to our Reaſon, that the King would not bring in a <hi>French</hi> Army, becauſe he did not go about it; for after all that a Malicious Induſtry could do, the P. of <hi>O.</hi> in a Defence of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, publiſhed by His Highneſs Command, confeſſes in the very firſt Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, no ſuch League with <hi>France</hi> could be proved.</p>
            <p>But now if the King of <hi>England</hi> could have had ſuch a Deſign, the King of <hi>France</hi> would not have concurred with him in it; and we may well conclude he would not.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he declined the Overture which the <hi>Dutch made him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Stubbe</hi>'s further juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the War with the United <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands. p. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to tranſport fifty thouſand of his Souldiers into any part of the King of</hi> England'<hi>s Dominion.</hi> Had the King of <hi>France</hi> been inclined to invade us, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> adviſed, and ſome feared, he would never have baulked an opportunity ſo fit for ſuch an Enterprize,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98365:3"/>for the <hi>Dutch</hi> made him the offer, when the old Rebels had almoſt put the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Confuſion again.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the King of <hi>France</hi> would not aſſiſt the K. of <hi>England</hi> in any ſuch Deſign, becauſe if he ſent any of his men to embroil us, he could not defend his Conqueſts upon the Continent; Nay, he would not be able to defend his own Kingdom againſt thoſe many Enemies that ſurround him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he would not, becauſe the welfare of <hi>France</hi> depends much upon the Proſperity and good Condition of <hi>England.</hi> We conſume more of their Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures than any Nation does, and they much of ours, ſo that the ballance of Trade is at leaſt much more equal betwixt us and the <hi>French,</hi> than betwixt us and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> from whom whatſoever we have, comes as it were out of the Huckſters hands. Thoſe Acts of Parliament which prohibit Commerce with <hi>France,</hi> ſtand upon this Notion, that a Trade with <hi>England</hi> is of mighty impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to <hi>France;</hi> and if ſtopping of Trade be cutting the Sinews of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, we may juſtly conclude that Monarch will not go about to hamſtring himſelf. A man therefore muſt be very ſubject to the Night Mare indeed that can apprehend Dragooning from <hi>France.</hi> Whatſoever his Zeal or his Ambition could prompt him to do upon his <hi>Hugonots</hi> at home, we may ſee that King either Repents, or has Policy enough not to purſue the point any further.</p>
            <p>By this time I preſume your Stomach is ſettled, and you out of danger of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Qualm for fear of <hi>France.</hi> I will now proceed to ſhew you, that your Miſtake is both groſs and dangerous, that upon this Revolution we ſhall have an happy and advantageous Alliance with the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we have any Advantage from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> it muſt be either in Protection to our Religion, or ſafeguard to our Country, or improvement of our Trade: But I will demonſtrate that your Expectation is vain and ill grounded, as to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe particulars, and that I hope will amount to a full Conviction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is improper and abſurd to expect protection for our Religion from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> either have no Religion at all themſelves, or pay no regard to it (I ſpeak in general, and with reſpect to their Government) for in the <hi>Indies</hi> they renounce Chriſtianity in ſo intire and horrid a manner,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Selge ea Conditione admittuntur (in Japonia) ut tenenter Praefecto Japonico tradere omnes Libros ſiquos ſecum adduxerint. Inſuper exercitiis Chriſtianae Religionis omnino ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinere, adeo quidem ut ne manus Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care ante Cibum vel poſt aſſumptum aude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. <hi>Varen. Deſcrip. Japoniae l. 1. cap. 26. p. 87.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Belgis diſſimulandam eſſe Religione &amp; pro Ethnicis quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> haberi a Magiſtratu japo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſiae. <hi>Varen. Deſcrip. Japoniae l. 2. cap. 11. pag. 225.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quamdiu apud Hollandos quidpiam quod Chriſtianiſmum redoleat, peragetur, nihil im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perrabunt. <hi>Varen. ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sic Leonard Campden, Belga apud. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. ibid. p. 226.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tractat. Theol. Polit. <hi>Cap. 5. p. 62.</hi> Edit. Hamburg. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Varen. Deſcrip. Japon. <hi>l. 2. cap. 11. p. 224.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they make no manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Religion at all, not ſo much as to pray for a Bleſſing upon the meat they eat, (if a Japanner be by,) or by lifting up their hands to intimate that they give God thanks for what they have eaten. If they have any Bible or Book of their Religion, they deliver them up.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they do ſo abſolutely abandon their Religion, or which is worſe, <hi>diſſemble it, that the</hi> Indians <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves take them for Heathens;</hi> and all this meerly for the ſake of Trade, for indeed the <hi>Indians would have nothing to do with them, nor let them live there but upon theſe Terms.</hi> 'Tis true the <hi>Indians,</hi> the <hi>Japoneſs</hi> more particularly, did in a ſavage manner deſtroy the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians that were there. But then all the guilt of that moſt Barbarous Perſecution, wherein ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands periſhed in divers manners, beyond all Example Cruel, muſt be charged to the account of the <hi>Dutch, who perſwaded the Emperour there, that the Chriſtians, whereof many were</hi> Spaniards, <hi>would thruſt him out of his Kingdom, and ſo instigated him to deſtroy them all, that the whole Trade might come to the Dutch,</hi> whom he had obſerv'd not to endeavour to propagate their Religion, when they had liberty, and would renounce it for gain ſake when he Commanded. I will give you one more remarkable inſtance of their Zeal, and that the God of this World is he only whom they care to ſerve.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98365:3"/>
            <p>In the Kingdom of <hi>Pegu,</hi> at a great Solemnity,<note place="margin">This Relation the diligent <hi>Stubbe</hi> had from the mouth of Mr. <hi>Briton,</hi> a Merchant of <hi>London,</hi> who was preſent at that horrid Solemnity, and a witneſs of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Piety. <hi>Stubbe</hi>'s further juſtification of the War with the United <hi>Netherlands, p. 77.</hi>
               </note> whereat the Emperour there Commanded them to attend, and to offer in Sacrifice ſome parched Rice to an Idol; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Portugueſes</hi> all refuſing, the ſecond man of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Factory, there briskly ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped forth, and offer'd the Rice in Sacrifice to the Idol, like a good <hi>Dutch</hi> Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>But that you may not think the heat of that Climate evaporates their Zeal, and exhales their Devotion, and by conſequence imagine that they are thus Heatheniſh only when they have croſs'd the Line, I will give you a proſpect of them nearer hand, and ſhew you what Spirit they are of in their own Country, and among their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there is a Toleration, or free Liberty of Exerciſe and Profeſſion to any, even the Rankeſt and moſt Blaſphemous Hereticks in the World, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it cannot properly be ſaid that there is any face of Religion among them, the whole being but an Oglio of Opinions. We have a good account of them from <hi>Beverningk,</hi> one of their own Embaſſadors, to the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> who ſaid to a great man in thoſe days, That it was impoſſible for <hi>England</hi> to continue a Republick, by reaſon of the violent Animoſities ariſing from the Differences of Religion; but in <hi>Holland, Chriſtianity had no ſuch effects upon the ſpirits of men;</hi> it might be ſaid indeed there were many <hi>Opinions in Holland, but one Religion, which was their Intereſt.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, all their Acts of State are with an Eye to that, only without any Conſideration of Religion, eſpecially of the Reformation. And for this point inſtead of many that may be produced, I will alledge three inſtances (1.) in ſuch Cities of <hi>Flanders,</hi> which being Conquered by theirs and the <hi>French</hi> Army, ſhou'd fall to the ſhare of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> even in thoſe Cities, upon a motion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> granted that the Profeſſion and Exerciſe of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religion</hi> ſhould be free and ſecure.<note place="margin">Leo ab Aitzma, <hi>p. 402 &amp; 403.</hi>
               </note> Had the <hi>Dutch</hi> had any regard to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, or concern for the Propagation and Support of Truth, they could not have been ſo indifferent (2.) if the <hi>Dutch</hi> would, in their Treaty of Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> have included the <hi>Hans</hi>-Towns of <hi>Germany,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Lubec, Bremen,</hi> and <hi>Hamburg;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo ab Aitzma, <hi>p. 578.</hi>
               </note> they had given great advantage to the Reformation in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and had contributed much to the preſervation or recovery of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> but they abſolutely refuſed it, let Religion ſhift as it could, for lucres ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by leaving thoſe Cities our, or expoſed, they expected to have all, or the chief of the Trade to themſelves. (3.) The laſt inſtance of their good affection to the Truth and Religion, is this, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt offered to ſend relief to the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> in hopes to procure ſome favour for the Reformation in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martin Schooc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius de Marit. Imperio, <hi>cap. 27.</hi>
               </note> but the <hi>Dutch,</hi> inſtead of promoting ſo Charitable a Deſign, <hi>ſent twenty Ships, Men of War, to aſſiſt the King of</hi> France, <hi>and ſo fruſtrated,</hi> and in fine, ruined that well intended Enterprize.</p>
            <p>By this time, I am confident you think the <hi>Dutch</hi> very unfit to be choſen the Guardians of our Religion, or that we have little concern for it, who offer to make ſuch a choice, it muſt indeed be a poor Diſh that is worthy only ſuch a Cover. I proceed now to ſhew you that we have much leſs reaſon to believe they will help to Defend our Country, or Improve our Trade.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Dutch</hi> are averſe to us, and will not defend our Nation. They have indeed enter'd into many Leagues with us, offenſive and defenſive, but it appears by overt Acts, that in all of them they were Colluſive, and without ſincerity,<note place="margin">See <hi>Stubbe's</hi> further juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the War with the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, p. 29, 30.</hi>
               </note> for they offer'd to aſſiſt the King of <hi>France</hi> to Invade <hi>England,</hi> as I told you before, and at ſeveral times have endeavoured to embroil us at home, as well as deſtroy us abroad.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they have given entertainment and protection to our Rebels, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98365:4"/>have aided them againſt their Lawful Soveraign, which is as high a violation as can be of the Law of Nature and Nations. I know they pretend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to excuſe themſelves, by ſaying, as a Free State they muſt receive all Perſons, but this is a meer pretence only, a Caſt of their Old Hipocriſie; for in the year 1622,<note place="margin">Leo ab Aitzma, <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </note> they entered in a League with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the 3d and 4th Articles of which League, expreſly bind them not to entertain, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, or aſſiſt any of that Kings Enemies. And in their League with the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo ab Aitzma, <hi>p. 839.</hi>
               </note> dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 28. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1653, by the 12th Article they bind themſelves to expel out of all their Territories, and not to receive again, or to <hi>harbour, or aſſiſt with Men, Money, or Proviſions, any of thoſe that were then accounted Enemies to the Commonwealth of England;</hi> and upon ſuch like Terms they made themſelves Allies and Confederates with our Notorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. But to ſhorten this Diſcourſe, which has already overgrown the ſize to which it was intended, I will demonſtrate to you that we are altogether in a wrong Box, while we propoſe to our ſelves an uſeful Amity with <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ingenious, but Unfortunate Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> for he miſerably end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his days in the <hi>Tower,</hi> having taken a turn in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> made this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation in the Reign of K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt:<note place="margin">Obſervations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the United Provinces, by Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury, p. 13.</hi> Lond. Print. <hi>1651.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That if the</hi> Spaniard <hi>were entirely beaten out of thoſe parts</hi> (and we know how little ſtrength he has there now) <hi>the Kings of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France <hi>would take as much pains to ſuppreſs the</hi> Dutch, <hi>as ever they did to raiſe them; for becoming our Enemies, they might be able to give us the Law at Sea and Eat us out of all Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The event has ſhewed how well grounded that Gentlemans Obſervation was; but that you may the better know what to expect from them, I will tell you what they have already done for us, which ſhews what their Morals are, and how far from all ſenſe of Honour and Gratitude.</p>
            <p>When we had helped them at no ſmall expence, of Men and Money, to ſhake off the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoke, and to raiſe themſelves into a Free State, and had encreaſed their Wealth by fixing our Staple among them, and ſuffered them to get ſtrength as well as Riches, by Fiſhing upon our Coaſts, they were not content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that Liberty which the Remiſneſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> too freely allow'd them, but with an unparallell'd inſolence and injuſtice they diſturbed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermen in our own Seas,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Secretary <hi>Naunton</hi>'s 2d Letter to Sir <hi>Dudley Carlton</hi> Embaſſ. at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secretary <hi>Coke</hi>'s Letter to Sir <hi>Will. Boſwel,</hi> the Kings Reſident at the <hi>Hague,</hi> both Printed at the end of <hi>Selden</hi>'s <hi>Mare Clauſ.</hi> tranſlated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucas de Liuda in Deſcript. Orbis.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>199,</hi> and Sir <hi>Will. Temple</hi>'s Obſerv. upon the United Provin. <hi>Cap. 6.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>driving their great Veſſels thro' their Nets. Nay, they ſoon grew to that Confidence, as to keep a Guard upon our Seas, and then to Project an Office and Company of Aſſurance, for the advancement of Trade; and withal, to Prohibit us free Commerce even within our own Seas, and to take our Ships and Goods, if we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not to their Placarts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Ingratitude would aſtoniſh us, but that we ſee their worldly Intereſt leads them to it. The Products of their Country are no way able to ſuſtain the Inhabitants, which are very Numerous, and therefore by Invincible Neceſſity, they are driven to look out for a Livelihood. Thus being by the Air and Indigence of their Country, and the Conſtitution of their Government diſpoſed to Avarice, it is become ſo rampant and governing a Vice among them, that it is both the Spring and the Standard of all their Actions, and upon this account, tho we were the Patrons, if not the Founders of their Commonwealth, our wonder at their proceedings muſt abate; ſince we are the Nation that are and can be their chiefeſt Rivals for Trade, upon which ſcore, purſuant to their Intereſt, they have always labour'd to ruine us, tho we preſerved them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stubbe</hi>'s fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vindic. of the War with the Unit. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, p. 68</hi>
               </note> Their Barbarities at <hi>Amboyna</hi> I paſs over, becauſe they were enough to make a Book by it ſelf. But in ſhort: Our Rich Trade into the <hi>Indies,</hi> at <hi>Japan, Amboyna, Banda,</hi> and the <hi>Molucco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is ruined, our Iſlands of <hi>Polerone, Polaway</hi> and <hi>Lantore,</hi> are unjuſtly ſeized into their hands, and the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98365:4"/>we ſuffer'd there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heylins</hi> Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megraph <hi>p. 919.</hi> A piece of Dutch Juſtice.</note> were computed in the year 1653 to amount to 1656233 pounds and upwards; for which, tho often call'd upon, they have never made us any ſatisfaction; but when they thought they ſhould be made to quit <hi>Poleron</hi> to us again, <hi>they cut down all the Clove-Trees there, which afforded the chief Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the place.</hi> They deſtroyed our Trade to <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> by ſeizing and deſtroying the Ships of Sir <hi>Will. Courteen</hi> and his Partners, for which wrongs the <hi>Engliſh</hi> demanded ſatisfaction, but in vain, by their Embaſſador Mr. <hi>St. Johns;</hi> as alſo the two Ships, the <hi>Katherine</hi> and <hi>Dragon,</hi> which they took and plunder'd, and inhumanly deſtroyed all the men to conceal the Piracy.<note place="margin">Stubbe<hi>'s ibid.</hi> p. 69.</note> And when His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty upon his Reſtauration Ratified a Treaty of Peace and Alliance with them, wherein he ſuffered many injuries done by them, to be utterly mortified and and extinguiſhed, contrary to their Articles, and the Rules of common Faith and Honeſty,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>George Downings</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>p. 8, 9,</hi> Lond. Print. <hi>1664.</hi>
               </note> new injuries were daily done us, and the deſigns of their <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-India</hi> Companies were ſtill carried on for the utter overthrow of all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade in thoſe parts of the World, as appeared by the bus'neſs of the Ships <hi>Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, Leopard,</hi> &amp;c. and in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> the <hi>Charles, James, Mary, Sampſon, Hopeful, Adventure, Speedwell,</hi> &amp;c. to the inoredible detriment of our <hi>Merchants;</hi> and which is yet worſe, to their <hi>Piracies</hi> they have added moſt amazing <hi>cruelty in deſtroying our men.</hi> Some of which they ſhut up in little <hi>Dungeons,</hi> to periſh with Famine,<note place="margin">Stubbe <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 69.</note> and the ſtench of Dead Carcaſſes, and their own Ordure, which was all the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding allowed them. Others the <hi>Dutch General</hi> made be put into Grates and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and carried them about, and Triumphantly ſhewed them to the <hi>Indian,</hi> to bring the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into contempt with them, that ſo they might not be able to Trade there. Laſtly, to make ſure work of all, and to put in Execution the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice given them by their <hi>Groninghen Profeſſor,</hi> in the year 1652, <hi>the States of</hi> Holland <hi>being then in League with the Commonwealth of</hi> England,<note place="margin">Ante omnia la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boremus Anglos toto mari expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lereilliuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium aſſerere. Mart. Schooc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins de Marit. Imper, <hi>cap. 28.</hi> Leo ab Aitzma, <hi>p. 804.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>without any Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of War, ſent their Admiral</hi> Van Trump <hi>with a Navy, to Burn and Deſtroy the Engliſh Fleet then lying in the Downs, but the Valour of the Engliſh defeated them, and by an abſolute Victory reduced them to a much humbler Figure, tho they ſoon returned to their wonted Inſolence and Piracy, and to practice all the arts of Treachery; for when they burnt our Ships at</hi> Chatcam, <hi>a Treaty of Peace was near concluded betwixt us and them.</hi> But I am weary in recounting ſo many things, which inſtead of honour, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, or humanity, ſpeak the greateſt baſeneſs that can be lodged in the breaſts of Men; and if what I have ſet down be not enough, do but conſult Sir <hi>George Downings</hi> diſcourſe upon a ſcandalous <hi>Dutch</hi> Memorial, by them clandeſtinely deſtributed to ſeveral Foreign Miniſters, but not given to his Majeſty's Envoy; it was printed at <hi>London, anno</hi> 1664. and the Depoſitions preſerved among the Records belonging to the Admiralty; and I am ſure you will find enough to make you and all <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> wiſh, that inſtead of making them our <hi>Patrons,</hi> there were a price by Act of Parliament ſet upon all <hi>Dutch-mens</hi> heads, as there is upon Wolves and Beaſts of Prey.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſure! but a Spirit of Infatuation fallen upon the Kingdom, and the Ruinous Deſigns of Revengeful and ill minded men, could have betrayed us into the hands and power of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who declare it to be for their advantage, and have accordingly laboured to deſtroy us, ever ſince they got (and that by our help) to be a Free-State. And a Deſign ſo deeply laid and founded upon their own intire Intereſt, we may be confident, now they have an Opportunity in their hands, they will not lay down till they have effectually ſecured us from Rivalling their Trade any more.</p>
            <p>How far we have given them an advantage to accompliſh our Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we not only ſee, but feel already; for all our Magazines are emptied of Arms and Ammunition; a Noble Stock of Timber which King <hi>James</hi> had provided to Build New Ships, and to Repair our Old, all embezzled, or Shipped of, and the Money of the Nation ſqueezed out of our hands by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive Taxes and impoſitions, when we have no Trade left whereby to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98365:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>get more. And in the laſt place, for a Conſummation of Diſgrace an Beggary to the Nation, like the Meſſengers of <hi>Jobs</hi> Calamities, we have freſh advice, That the <hi>Mogol</hi> (by the Inſtigation of the <hi>Dutch</hi>) is now fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Bumbay,</hi> the Chief of the Two Remaining Factories which the <hi>Dutch</hi> had left us in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies:</hi> and ſo all that Rich and Noble Trade is at the point to be abſolutely loſt, becauſe we are now in no Condition to ſend thither any Re-inforcement. At home our Calamities increaſe, and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation comes Rolling upon us like a mighty Wave; for none can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible Now, that it was but a fond Imagination, to believe giving the Crown to the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> would endear us to him, or give him a Tenderneſs over us, like that of a Rightful and Hereditary King: ſince he ſpared not one ſo near of Kin as our King was to him, how can we expect he ſhould have Bowels of Compaſſion for us? No one ever truſted, or long careſſed a Traitor; and ſince we have been capable of deſerting our Rightful King, and ſhewed our ſelves as wavering and unſteady as the Sea that ſurrounds us, I ſee no Reaſon to believe he will put any Confidence in us, or truſt us with ſo much power as may preſerve our juſt Liberties and Properties, for fear it ſhould annoy him. Now they have given as much Money as can be, he has diſmiſſed his Parliament, which in difficult Times was wont to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a kind of Pledge, or the beſt Security betwixt the Prince and People; and he is getting over what Forreigners he can, as unwilling that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould earn their own Money, or be truſted to defend their own Countrey.</p>
            <p>As to the Church, I perceive you are a little jealous grown to be, not only for the Act paſſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to aboliſh Epiſcopacy, but for the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Commiſſion, which put it into the hands of a few men, to new mould our Church, and at the ſame time ſuffer it to be robbed or deprived of ſo many Excellent Biſhops, who gave ſuch Noble Teſtimonies to the Truth againſt Popery. I muſt confeſs, ſuch Proceedings are like to render both our Religion ſafe, and our Church triumphantly glorious. But as men ſeldom know how to value a Bleſſing as they ought, till they feel the want of it; ſo I hope the Varniſh is off, and the Miſt ſo far cleared, that all men may ſee theſe Dire Effects of our glorious Revolution, and in time become ſenſible of the ſad Preſages of the Nations Ruine, unleſs prevented, by Reſtoring the Government to its Old Conſtitution, by bringing back the King, who is ſenſible of his Miſtake, and ſo are his Adviſers too; and we may be ſure he will try no more Concluſions in State. All the World ſees, the Grievances of his Reign are not Redreſſed in this, but many new ones added; ſo that if we were in the Frying-Pan before, we are now leapt into the Fire. Whereas, were the King at home again, and we true to our Religion, and firm to our Conſtitution, as good Chriſtians we may, and as good Subjects we ought, we need not fear the Gates of <hi>Rome,</hi> no, not of Hell it ſelf. But if the Will of God be ſo, that we muſt ſuffer, why not by the Papiſts as well as by the Fanaticks, who are no leſs vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or Blood-thriſty; or by the <hi>French</hi> rather than by the <hi>Dutch;</hi> for the <hi>French</hi> have ſome Intereſt in our Preſervation, and have ſome Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but the <hi>Dutch</hi> have neither. If you have any more Scruples, I will not doubt, if I may know them to procure you ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now God of his Mercy, remove the Judgments we already feel, and avert thoſe further Puniſhments which the Reigning Sins of this Nation (Perjury and Rebellion, Fraud and Violence) do lowdly call for, and preſerve the Church of</hi> England <hi>as by Law Eſtabliſhed, from the Attempts and Deſigns of all its Enemies.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
